great
接下来我会从一些基础的东西讲起
这样其他朋友们看到我发的tweet进来（直播）的时候
也不会错过太多内容
如果你之前已经安装过rust的话
接下来的应该对你难度不大
yeah 我接下来想谈一点
关于rust的安装以及上手
装好需要的一些工具，并且能运行起来
当你把需要的东西装上并跑起来以后
你就可以和我一起play起来了
如果你已经完成了相关的安装，别担心
讲完这些不会花太多时间的
我们要去的第一个地方是 rustup.rs
rustup.rs 就是一个简单的网站
它会检测你使用的电脑
还有现在你在用的操作系统
之后会显示一行脚本给你
你可以运行它来安装rustup
在百分之90的情况下这就是你想要的
如果你用的是特殊的linux发行版
有一些特殊的安装要求，可能会遇到困难
你应该按你的linux发行版安装软件的方法去做
我现在用的操作系统是nix os
正好 nix 就是一个有特别的安装方法的系统
我很高兴能分享我的方法，如果有谁也在用nix os
我可以分享我的nix shell
但是总的来说，你访问 rustup.rs之后
你应该就能直接复制粘贴然后把rust安装上了
我已经安装好了这些
我只是想要给大家展示一下rustup.rs
如果之前没见过的话
在windows上 在mac上
还有大多数linux发行版上
这是安装rust的一个好选择
我之后会用vs code
我相信大家都有安装了
至少也听说过
如果你还没有安装它
这并不是唯一的
你可以使用的工具
应该说不是唯一的ide
你可以安装以后用来编辑
rust代码的，但它用起来
挺好
就像我说的，我将会使用它
告诉你如何设置
vs code 但我也想提一下
还有 intellij rust
这也是另一个适合人们使用的好工具
that
你知道也许他们更喜欢intellij风格
我已经用过几次了，有人告诉我说
它非常好的
我应该首先向大家推荐的
而不是推荐我自己的设置，所以
你知道
无论哪种，你知道也许可以同时尝试，或者如果
你看一下
嗯，两个网站，看看哪一个感觉
对你来说更好
更符合你已经习惯的工作流
关于intellij的一个好东西是
intellij
rust ide support
是，它实际上是相当
复杂，所以他们有像
重构
他们有相当好的静态分析
宏扩展
我不打算顺便说一下，我不打算
谈论宏的问题，这是
更
关注初学者的视频，但如果你开始深入
Rust更认真一些的时候，你会想
你就会希望有一些东西能帮助你处理这些问题。
宏，因为它是
这绝对是语言中的一个领域
开发相关工具很吃力，因此
调试你的宏和其他东西也
往往要花很多时间，所以任何你能找到的
工具支持
真的很有帮助，它有自动完成功能
我们在vs code插件中也一样会看到
但是，嗯，任何这些
跳出来的功能，冉你感觉
是的，我真的很想
我真的很喜欢其中的一些功能
假设你用了几个星期Rust
然后你就会想，我真的很希望我的Ide能做这个
也许intellij就是你的理想选择。
所以我只想提一嘴
因为可能你想要的东西
与我正在使用的设置有一点不同
但这是我会用到的设置
如果你想和我一起玩耍一下
所以我已经安装了 VS Code
但我要告诉你之后的步骤
dog jones提到了Clion
CLion是另一个你可以用的Ide
有一个Rust插件可以下载
所以你知道的， 只要你觉得用着顺手就行。
就是随便到处点一点， 看看有什么功能
并找到设置
对， 所以浏览器里面的内容还有什么可说的吗
在我们开整之前 ，让我想想
我觉得这样好， 我就把浏览器开着挂在后台吧
所以我们可以在需要时跳回它
但我现在要把它隐藏起来
找个地方放一下
所以我们现在是在 VS Code 中
嗯，我已经设置好了VS Code
但我要告诉你如何设置VS Code
好让你知道
比方说，这是一个新的安装
我进入它的第一件事是
我将点击这个左手边写着 "扩展 "的地方。
然后我将在顶部搜索 "rust"
现在，当你这样做时，会看到好多搜索结果
你注意到， 至少前两个
有相当多的下载数量
你知道超过10 000， 所以真的
这两个里你可以选一个安装
我倾向于使用的是名为 Rust Analyzer 的插件。
Rust Analyzer 是一种拓展的Ide支持
所以它不一定是作为 rust 的一部分来打包的
但当你安装这个插件
它将会下载一个扩展包， 这将是 rust analyzer服务器 的二进制包
然后这将在你的系统的后台运行
而 rust analyzer 插件会与跑在本地的 rust analyzer服务器 通信
然后给你
提供相应的Ide的支持
我们会看到， 随着我们往下走
但 rust analyzer 是我要推荐的
我们可以看到， 现在它是pre1.0版本，
所以你可能会发现，每一次在一段时间内
你可能需要重新启动它或其他什么来保持它的运行
但我发现它对于小型项目。
还有中等规模的项目
呃......它往往是无懈可击的
当你进入真正的大项目时
然后它就好像每隔一段时间就会出点小问题，你得重启一下什么的
在这种大项目上稍微有点痛苦了有时候
但我想说的是，基本上
这是一个相当可靠的
在起步阶段这是个相当可靠的插件
所以我已经安装了，你看
我这里没有安装的按钮
所以一旦安装完毕，它就会去获取 Rust语言服务器。
额， 不对是Rust Analyzer服务器， Rust language 服务器是以前用的了
一旦安装了Rust Analyzer， 它就会在后台运行。
然后它可能会让你重新启动VS Code
或类似的操作
一旦它被重新启动，你的环境
就和我现在的一样了
所以现在， 你已经装上了rustup
然后 rustup 会提供给你
rust编译器和与之配套的一系列工具
我们已经得到了Ide支持，通过
你知道的 安装VS Code和rust analyzer
这两个安装操作
你需要跟着我完成的
这样才能跟着我继续下面的直播
嗯，好的，一旦装好了rust analyzer
你需要做的配置真的不多。
呃，让我们看看，我是不是在骗你？
让我快速检查一下
我正在努力回忆是否有任何设置， 我做了什么？
可能与默认值有不同的。
嗯，我确实要确保
启用了保存时的检查（check on save）
所以每次我保存
每次我保存这个项目时
然后它就会在后台重建。
它将重新检查这个项目
然后给我任何错误和其他东西
所以我更喜欢它在每次保存时进行检查。
我想另一件事是，我通常会检查
和默认情况不同的是
是格式
是的，我检查了这个
这也是VS Code特有的设置
intellij可能有不同的设置
但在vs code中， 我开启了自动格式化
我们点击这个
原因是
虽然这个直播里不会仔细讲
但其中有一件事， 随着rustup安装的一个东西是
rust的格式化工具（rust formmater）
这给了Rust代码一个标准的格式
所以它更容易阅读，
更容易审阅，就像如果你要发送一个PR
大多数经常用Rust的人都会
习惯了rust的格式
标准的Rust格式
所以我肯定会建议你选上这个，这样每一次你保存的时候
它就会重新格式化你的代码
顺便说一下，呃，其中一个好东西
关于这个自动格式化
是如果它没有格式化你的代码
当你点击保存的时候
那么一种情况可能是解析器的问题
另一种就是你代码里有错误
有点像是提醒你哪里写错了
我需要关闭一个括号
我需要在某个地方关闭它的圆括号
一旦你这样做了，它就会顺利格式化了
你就感觉， 好， 至少没有明显的语法错误了。
现在我可以让剩下的部分继续下去了
是的，所以安迪提到了这一点
要确保你安装（rust官方插件和rust analyzer）其中一个
我认为这是个好主意
所以你可以选一个试一试
如果不喜欢它，先把它卸载掉
然后再安装另一个
不要像是点了这个的安装然后又继续点另一个
安装 安装 安装
然后希望它工作，因为有些
其中有重叠的功能
所以如果你同时运行它们，它们会发生冲突
在同一时间
是的，这是个好问题
其他可有可无的东西我都说了，我想
这就是一般的
这两个配置选项
我会检查的
确保它在保存的时候检查代码
确保它在保存时进行格式化
这让我能够有
非常合理的信心
我看到所有的实时错误和
我的代码也被格式化了
正确的
所以doctrines问到编译的问题
Rust的编译器创建了一个exe文件
因为Rust是一种系统级编程语言
所以我们说的是像C或C加加的东西。
它确实是为编写
真正利用你系统性能的应用程序程序而创造出来的
所以当你建立一个rust的项目在
比如说windows，你会得到一个应用程序
级别的东西，这是一个EXE
有一些方法，可能你也知道，不一定是编译成EXE
正如其他人刚刚指出的那样
cargo run 是另一个选择
所以，让我们真正开始讨论一下
一些随rust安装的工具
因为我们在接下来将使用这些工具
所以我首先要做的是
对不起，有点早，我的喉咙有点
还没睡醒
所以我在我的源码目录中，我正在进行
启动一个新的项目
所以我们就把这个项目叫做嗯
stream，所以在这个
在这个命令行中，所以一旦我已经
我已经运行了让rustup
我已经安装了所有的工具，然后我
可以运行这个 cargo 命令
cargo是, 它是
像一些不同的命令
合并在一个命令中，它的工作是能够
不仅仅是构建你的应用程序，所以它可以
构建所有的rust
嗯，所有的rust源代码，它也将
去为你获取项目的依赖
比方说，你依赖其他一些
他们称它们为crate(rust库的名称)，
你知道的就是一个模块，另一个组件
在某处（比如crate.io或者github上）
它将去安装并帮你构建它
并让它准备好，这样它就可以链接到你的
应用中
它可以做 嗯，我想你也可以检查一下
比如说
像过时的依赖
像这样的
嗯，你还可以用插件扩展cargo，
让它有更多的功能
所以它是一个非常强大的工具，真的
厉害
某种程度上是处理开发中很多任务的的一个百宝箱
你将会使用
作为一个开发者，使用Rust进行开发
然后这个我将要做的就是
运行 cargo new
这将会创建一个新的rust项目
然后就得到了
一个基本的模板，一个开始的项目
将使用
嗯，让我们继续下去，看看那个
而我要做的是，我将打开
我刚刚创建的项目，我将用vs code打开那个
你会发现在vs code中，如果你不是
熟悉它
我没有打开任何项目文件或
诸如此类的东西
我所做的就是打开我的目录
刚刚创建的 嗯
有一种相当于我们的
项目文件
这就是这个cargo.toml
所以你可以看到，嗯，这里
我们在"stream package"里，这里是我的
版本
一切，呃，当你使用 cargo new的时候，
它默认为
0.1，让你知道，我想他们是
让你从
非常基本的版本开始
当然还有像who i am和这个
edition(rust编译器大版本，类似C++的 C++17，20之类的标识)
是说你想要使用的Rust语言的版本
在这个项目中，然后我们使用
rust 2018，所以这是最新的（现在是2021了）
rust的版本
顺便说一下，今年晚些时候我相信
将会有另一个版本问世
所以，如果你看到这个变化
今年晚些时候，这是因为你知道
我们有一个新的版本
会在语言中做出一些变动
但如果你想跟上我的视频
在新的rust版本的出来后
如果你担心
关于任何不兼容的问题，你可以直接
设置edition到2018
而我们在stream中所做的一切
将在任何的时间都正常工作
这个cargo.toml的另一部分是
依赖的声明
所以像我之前说的，你可以添加
依赖关系到你的项目
然后cargo会去获取它们
并为你构建它们
我们可能会增加一些，随着
我们的项目继续进行
然后，另外一个cargo new创建的东西是
gitignore文件
这很好，我想我们是与时俱进的
你知道的
我们正在使用git
它说它将会忽略掉
target目录，target目录将会存放
所有的构建产物
所以，一旦我打出 cargo build
它就会把构建过程的东西都放到/target中,
然后main.rs
是它创建的最后一个东西
而这是实际的rust代码
好了，这就是我们的hello world，呃
我们将在下面讨论这个问题
等一下，我需要看两眼
直播的弹幕
rust up docs也很有帮助，因为它
打开完整的
由rustup保存在本地的rust文档
谢谢你，安迪，这真是个有用的点。
嗯，是的，其他的一些cargo的功能
是，你可以打开
文档
你可以运行相当于一个java doc的程序
在你的代码上，这样你就可以为你的
rust代码添加文档（doc string）
然后在它上面运行一个cargo命令，然后
然后它将生成HTML文档
基于你的文档注释
在代码中
而且你可以做测试，所以rust和cargo
有内置的测试工具
所以你可以使用 cargo test，
它将会运行所有的测试，在你的
应用里
是的，很好，所以让我们来
谈一谈
这个hello world 嗯
呃，这很有趣，因为第一件事
我想说的是，我不打算
马上讨论printline
这和所有其他语言中的println差不多，
但是， 我们是在main函数
而这个 fn 是一个你会
注意到的， 在rust中
有......有......有一些缩写
我想 fucntion 这个词实在
太长了，不方便打出来
所以他们使用fn，所以它说是函数
main它没有参数，然后
这里有一个代码块，它将运行
而这个代码块确实调用了
某种打印函数，
伴随这个很奇怪的
最后的感叹号，这是一个
宏（macro）
同样，我也不会深入讲这个
在这个视频中
但是，这允许它是一个有点
比一般的函数更高级的
它可以采取多于一个
变量， 所以它是非常高级的功能
它可以接受可变数量的
参数，而唯一的方法是要做到这一点
的唯一方法是使用一个宏，所以
这就是
这就是为什么println是一个宏的简短原因
在这个例子中，尽管没有
额外的参数
它只是一般的形式，所以它其实接受
n个参数
好的，那么这将打印出Hello world
让我们实际运行这个项目
所以我们可以看到这有几种方法
我们可以运行这个
所以我可以通过在命令行输入cargo run来运行这个
如果我这么做，它将会
做的是它要构建它
然后，一旦它完成了构建它
它将为我运行它
这是嗯，用于大量的调试工作
场景，你知道的，你想调整
你想要的东西，只是得到一个快速
运行，看看是否
是正确的，你知道你会使用很多
的cargo run
你也可以构建那些产物
通过 cargo build
你会注意到它已经是它的
已经构建好了，所以那次cargo run只花了
不到半秒钟的时间
而这次是一百分之一秒的时间，因为这些
产物是由cargo run构建的
所有产物（二进制，依赖包的二进制，可执行文件等）都在/target目录中
在这种情况下（cargo run），我建立了一个
debug构建
所以如果我们打开/target/debug，我们会看到
有一个
在目录中有个 stream
同时有相当数量的其他东西
rust的作用
我想说的是， cargo 会为你构建
你的examples和
和你的依赖关系等，所以/target里
有一堆其他的目录
东西
但我们真正关心的主要事情是
是 stream这个二进制文件
就在这里
所以如果我运行这个/target/debug/stream
我得到同样的结果，所以这就是
如果在WINDOWS中，cargo构建的将是一个.exe文件
在linux中，这只是一个可执行文件
一个二进制
在Mac OS里也是如此
好吧，让我快速扫描弹幕看看
如果有任何问题
嗯，有一个
哦，我想你没有谈到这个
关于这个
但你提醒了我，你可以做
一种实时的构建
开启一个实时构建活动，我正在尝试
回忆这个是怎么做的
我想有一个cargo插件可以用在这里
在那里你可以
你知道要求cargo保持运行和
所以每当你保存时，它就会重新编译构建项目
并给你返回结果
如果我能想起这个插件的名字，我会
迟些时候告诉你们
好了，现在我们已经我们已经做了cargo run
和cargo build，这就是真正的
循环
是我们要做很多事情的地方。
我们的很多工作
正如我所提到的，还有一些测试，所以我
可以打出
#[test]和
my_test函数，我们将只是assert
在这个特殊的情况下是true
注意实际上呃，其中一件事
我觉得vs code特别方便的是
是，你知道我可以从vs code中运行
我可以运行这个函数，所以它将
构建并运行它
酷，我也可以运行测试，所以它将
构建并运行测试
然后这就是cargo test的输出
看起来像
所以我已经得到了你知道它说运行一个
测试并且通过了一个测试
如果我把这里改成
false然后运行测试
它会编译然后说哦这个失败了
它会告诉你哪一个失败了
所以很多测试
都是这种形式的
这只是一种告诉rust
这个函数属于测试套件的方法
而不是应用程序本身
所以你可以这样标记你的测试
然后当
当cargo编译它的时候它会知道
rust编译器会寻找
所有这些测试用例
然后把它们放到一个可执行文件里
运行然后测试
所有的测试给你
我没有流文件
可以在这里发截图吗
当然可以啊
我想我只是分享
我的代码所以我可以在流之外点击它
对了"cargo watch"谢谢你
那是
那个可以实时重建的
然后
检查结果的
当你保存的时候它会自动为你重建的
[Music]
great
and i'm kind of deciding in real time
how much of rust i need to show in the first example
let's actually show
let's start with numbers first
and then we'll go to strings
and the reason i'm starting with numbers first
is that strings are decidedly more complex
and so let's build to that
i don't think they're so complex that you can't understand them
but there's a few more steps to them than to like a simple number
so we'll start with the number first
and then
we'll use this number and then we'll go from there
so it's not end
sorry i keep going back and forth
between languages is64
ides i gotta love them when they
highlight and kind of warn me that i'm
typing the wrong thing
all right so we're gonna print um hello to number here
and then i'll call the greet function from here
all right let's get our terminal back
bash there we go
so what i've done here is created a new function
and it's taking a number this is a assigned a 64-bit integer i-64
and then i'm just using this as a
parameter here you can see where i said
earlier that print line
you can use it to pass arbitrary number
of parameters
and that's really going to be based on
what's in the string
so this string says there's one argument
that's going to get passed in
and then just put it here just like a
format string
and then i pass in x
so yeah the next thing
that we should show off is
okay let's just talk about strings let's
get it away let's get it out of the way
um so strings are
there's two kinds of strings
i guess you could say a string
which is the like an array of characters
uh ray of bytes in memory that will
be the the string that's written out so
the the hello to my number or hello
world
all right so that's a string of bytes
that can be interpreted as characters to
write to the screen
right so that is a string
so i'm going to make a string
my greeting
hello world
and you'll see that this is something
slightly different
so this says anster we're gonna we're
gonna get back we're gonna come back to
that
but before we do that i'm gonna do this
first
so what i've done is i've made a string
this string i've said turn this string
into a capital string capital s string
and then i'm going to pass that into
here string
hello to hello world all right let's see
all right so this string capital s
string
is living in the heap somewhere
so i've got the memory that is for
this particular function on the stack
and then i've got the heap which is the
memory i allocate from my application
so string is living it's taking this
turning it into something that's living
on the heap and then
i'm calling greet with that string
there's also and stir
which we saw a little bit earlier so if
i take this off
i get this version and this is just
saying that there is a
what's called a string slice there is
two
like a pointer and a length that points
somewhere in memory
who knows where we don't know where but
we are going to
point to that and then hand that
information
to the function and then it's going to
to print this out
so capital s string and and stir
are the two ways that you'll see strings
in russ code
and i just want to show them here we'll
see this ampersand
later and we'll get to learn why it's
ampersand stir
and like what that kind of means but i
just wanted to show the two styles of
strings
because when you're seeing rust code
you'll see you'll see both styles
depending on the situation
yep all right so that's kind of
functions
um something that we haven't done
is to see a result uh do we want to
sure why not
so we'll say this is let's say this is
name
jt
and then we'll get our result which is
that and then we'll print this to the
screen
and that needs to be
can't find oh yeah oops name
there you go incidentally
um another pitch for ide is having
having the live error checking and then
you can hover and see what the errors
are
key all right so
i i changed our example just a little
bit so we can see a return value
we see i've created a jt string
anster technically i've passed that into
a function called greet
so that comes in format just it's like
print line
almost identical to print line but print
line does the additional step of writing
out to the screen
format just creates a string from what
you're giving it so it's kind of
the same format that we're using for
print line
i pass an argument and it's going to
create a string for us
notice i haven't i didn't say return
this is just muscle memory i could have
said it this way
and got the same answer
but one of the quirks i guess you could
say about rust
is that you don't have to say return for
the last thing
in the function or the last the last
expression that would be evaluated in a
function
you can just leave the return off and
leave the semicolon off
and the semicolon does matter if you
leave the semicolon off and the return
off
it treats this value it'll run this
value
and then return the result of this
so it's a slightly subtle but i also
wanted to mention it because it is
definitely something you will see in
rust code in the wild
is that people will leave off the
semicolon and leave off the return
and just assume that this last value
will return from the function
so this will create format creates
capital s string so it's creating
in the heap it's creating some string
memory
allocating it enough space to write out
this this formatted string
and then handing us back the um
as we'll see and sending back the
ownership of this capital string so the
the the ability to own this thing and
once we have the result i just go ahead
and do what we did before i just print
the result
that we got
are our macros like dunder methods
in python um i'm not familiar enough
with python to know what the similarity
between
rus methods or rust macros and
dunder methods are sorry
are gender methods related to being able
to pass
like a number of arguments
like any number of arguments to the
function
all right so that is functions and
function calls of course we can have
like multiple parameters here
so i could have had like a y um
and then use the y in here so that kind
of follows a pattern if you're used to
other programming languages
no surprises
the next thing i want to talk about is
so there's like a whole bunch of rust
topics that we could go
into i'm going to just kind of kind of
touch
on enough that we can then explore a
little bit deeper
but the next thing i want to talk about
is structs
so let's say the classic one that i
always saw
in programming books growing up was
employee
which sounds very corporate but uh sorry
we got an employee we'll have the name
of the employee
we'll use string string tends to be
easier to work with because there isn't
any
uh any additional ownership things we
need to think about this ampersand
and again i'm kind of foreshadowing this
ampersand
gives us a hint that there is more
sophisticated lifetime stuff or
ownership stuff going on underneath the
surface
string does not alright string is just a
value it's pointing out into heap memory
that's all we need
and whoever has this owns this and
that's nice and simple
we'll have an id that's that's also
a sure i-64
so we can create um we can create an
employee
so let's do that i'm going to get rid of
this greet function
but we'll probably bring it back in a
second but just for now
keep it simple we can create an employee
by saying employee
equals now the first way that you can
create it
is to say employee and then
open curly and then start writing values
in at this point
so stream urine here now
and then we'll give an ide of 101
sure notice when i hit save
oh yeah that is two string
when i hit save it did the reformat
that's again because the vs code has
that setting
but it also is nice because i know that
this parses correctly
um and it reads a bit better now that
it's formatted
so i've created an employee we now have
an employee
it's got a name i'm using again the
capital s
form of string here so i use the dot to
string so that converts
this into a capital s string
and then i give ide a number and i have
an employee
you'll notice that once i do this i
create a
structure but i'm trying to print out
the structure and and russ is like
saying
um you can't do that
oh this is result let's try employee
which will also be true that
there's a whole bunch of gobbledygook
things um
but what it's trying to say in fact
actually if we try to build down here i
think we'll see it a little bit better
one of the one of the things that vs
code
and internal ides struggle with is that
when russ has a lot of information it
doesn't necessarily format it well so if
you see something that like
in the hover is just it's just too much
too much to parse go ahead and do the
build
on the command line if you want to get a
little bit more information
so this is saying a lot of stuff some of
which we're going to talk about
in a little bit later but um
i just let's just quickly look at it so
it's saying
employee cannot be formatted with the
default formatter
and that kind of makes sense right we've
got a format string
it's saying take in this value
and then just put it into the string and
it's saying i don't know you've got a
struct
i need a string i have no idea how to
turn your struct into a string
and then there's some more information
and as you get more advanced and rust
this will kind of make sense it's saying
you know there's certain things that you
can
certain definitions that you can create
certain um
traits as well we'll kind of look into
traits here in a bit
you know things that you can describe
about your types
so that russ can do more with them
but we haven't done that yet we just
made a struct
and in making this direct
well that's it there's not enough
knowledge to actually print this out
so there's a couple ways that we can
handle this
the first way is just to actually work
with the fields themselves
so i could say
name and then
dot name
and once i hit save here let's go ahead
and run this
and then you see it says okay cool as
long as i can reach
into the structure and get to values
that
russ knows how to print then we're okay
but the problem was actually having that
whole structure it had no idea how to
print that
um yeah some of the comments andy points
out that there are different ways that
you can turn
one string into like a an and stir
into a string so there's like an
alternate method where you can say
string new and then pass in a string
like
hello and this does um
string from sorry not string new string
from
so this does the same thing as dot
tostring
just um you know matter of preference if
you prefer seeing it this way
definitely go for that
i have to be gentle with my water
there's like a cord for my microphone i
have to dodge around it okay
so we've reached into uh our string
our struct sorry our struct got the
string out
um we could do the same thing for ide
you'll notice i've got a little squiggle
rust is smart enough to know hey you've
used some of these fields but not all of
them
so that's pretty handy if you you need
to
find how to you know where you can
refactor your structs to remove stuff
that isn't getting used um
another way to print out the employee
and again this is a bit of foreshadowing
is that i can say derive debug
and i'll use a slightly different
format string here
and this is going to use what's called a
debug
format instead of a display format
a little bit in the weeds display is the
default and debug is
um more of an kind of an exploded view
into what you're looking at it's
intended like it says for debugging
so if i run this you'll see
um i see my greeting name of course now
it's not just the name it's the whole
thing
employee capital e employee semicolon or
curly and then the two fields
so if you're doing logging if you're
doing
print line debugging which i love
uh i'm a bit of old-school person i
don't really use the debugger that much
i do tend to use a lot of
print line debugging and then being able
to mark
structures as debug gives me the
opportunity to easily log them out or
easily print them to the screen
and see the contents um let me show you
one
one quick one this one's really nice so
this
magic spell it's like this cubert line
uh gives us a yet another way of doing
debug printing and this one's a little
bit nicer so it will
kind of pretty print out that value
for some for a small struct it's maybe
not as necessary you could kind of see
it on one line
but i found that as your structs get
bigger it's nice to kind of pretty print
them so you can see a little bit better
yeah so someone just asked are we gonna
go over dependencies yeah we'll
definitely
we'll definitely add some dependencies
to cargo tunnel so you can see what that
looks like in practice
they'll probably come a little bit later
all right so this is struxx being able
to define our structs and i kind of
hinted at
some new abilities that strucks will
have as we understand rust a little bit
better
these aren't required like you can start
more simply i just want to show like
once
you're at the point where you're like
well
i'm kind of stuck i don't know what's in
the structure i want to at least mention
the debug stuff so you can get
and get some interesting debug out of it
alright so we're back to this example
so that's structures in a nutshell
there's more
more to structures once we start talking
about traits or generics
but as the basic level of structs like
that's
that's abstract pretty plain and simple
um
do we want to talk about
yeah let's let's go ahead i've i kind of
made a list i'm going to stick to the
list
even though i'm tempted to to riff a bit
but let's
let's talk about the next thing on the
list which is enums
so we have employee and that is a way of
grouping
you know multiple fields and being able
to reference them
by like dotting into them another way
that you commonly structure your data
and ross is through an enum
so what would be a good example of an
enum
um
let's say
uh is true
equals true or false
okay hold on a second
i'm trying to think of like a good um
yeah let's do that so there's like true
false sorry for the what was that like
haskell or something
you can see that over the years i've
done way too many languages
all right what's our warning here oh
yeah it's never used
okay so we've got um an enum
and an enum is basically letting us talk
about
one of instead of being
all of these values like a struct is
like all of these fields is
one value an enum is one of these values
is the value
and you don't know until you ask
so let's look at what that looks like in
practice
so we have this is true enum
so we'll say my value equals
is true and you you notice instead of
dot we use colon colon does
whether you use dot or whether you use
colon colon there is kind of a rule
behind it
around is it a kind of a static value or
is it a
runtime thing i find that you're just
going to have to play with it a little
bit to get
the kind of the hunch of whether it's a
a dot dot a colon colon or a dot
um but for enums enums use the colon
colon
right so we've set this in we've picked
one of the enum values so this one we've
picked
false and then
once we've made this value you see that
its type
is this is tree them so at this point
we don't know which one it is is it
false or is it true we no longer know
after this point in terms of the type
system
and so what we need to do is to match
and match is going to look at this value
and kind of unpack it for us so that we
can do
one for each case for each case and that
enumeration
we can do something and uh something
different with the value
so it says uh this is mitching missing
match arm
that's just a way of saying this match
needs to actually satisfy or or
check for every case in that enumeration
so let's start to check for each of
these cases
we can say is true so for the true case
we can say print line true
and then is true false
print line false
and then we'll run this
so this gives us a way of doing
i mean a lot of different ways of
working
with languages namely like a more of a
state machine
or more of a when you're in a situation
where it could be one of a set of states
then an enumeration is a very common way
to represent that in rust
so being able to get a value and then
pass that value in
not knowing what the state of it is but
then
being able to use the match statement to
query
what the values actual you know state is
underneath the surface
and then executing some code based on
what the different possibilities are
one of the nice things about
enumerations and rus
is that they can carry along some
information
so for example this true
could carry along with it uh an i64
like we were doing earlier so let's say
maybe this is like
if there's an ide that goes along with
it it will say yes there is one
and it will give you this this number
and if there isn't it just says okay
that's false so we've changed this to
say
that um it has kind of a if you will
kind of a payload
like that might be a
silly way of saying it but you can kind
of see what i'm saying like this this
extra data
is writing along with the fact that it's
true so once we match with true
we can get this data out and you'll
notice here that we're erroring
and the error is saying yeah okay cool
it's true but in order for you to
actually pattern match this you have to
not only
match that is true but you have to do
something with the data
we can ignore it using underscore that's
totally one way we can do that
or we can use a variable and once we use
a variable
it will take that value bind it to that
variable
so now x is equal to what was contained
in
that payload and then we can just print
that out
if i can write my curlys
all right it's still warning us that
true isn't being used let's actually use
it
so we can see this payload come out
if we run this we'll say true100
so this is actually quite a bit
different than
languages that have like typescript or
whatever
that have enumerations where
it's only the true or false it's not any
of the payload
and the payload actually is
excuse me is one of the more important
parts about
about um pattern matching and
languages like rust because not only do
you get the state
like the kind of the the the name of the
state you also get the data that goes
along with the state
so if you want to use this again for
state machines or something then you can
have information in there
that will actually make this far more
powerful
than just knowing what state you're in
and rust actually let me pause for a
second any questions about anything i've
i've talked about up to this point we
kind of talked about structs and enums
maybe any questions about structs and
enums
are there other pattern matching
languages than rust yeah so russ comes
from a heritage
of functional programming languages if
you've
ever had a chance to check out haskell
or ocamel
these languages have generally more
sophisticated pattern matching
because it's such it's like a
how you work with data is so integrated
with this
idea of of being able to have not only a
state
but data along with that state so yeah
other functional languages do tend to
have more sophisticated pattern matching
yep cool i'll just keep plugging away
so that's enums so rust uses this
uh enums be like in a way that
give it the ability to do error checking
an error reporting without any
exceptions
so there's no exceptions like if you
come from
say javascript or c sharp languages like
that
you're used to being able to throw an
exception and then to catch an
exception and do something in those
cases that's that's the kind of common
way that you write code in those
languages
in rust rust is
a much more what's called like
value-based languages
instead of thinking about exceptions and
non-local kind of like returning to some
other
spot rather than the return location for
your function
russ just returns from the function
that's all it does
but when it returns it returns in such a
way that
you know if that function is succeeded
or not
and you can work with the value let's
actually kind of
unpack what i just said through an
example
let's get rid of our structs and enums
and get us back to
writing a function so we're going to
write a function and this function is
going to be
um something like it's going to do some
work
and it's going to return a result that
result will either be a string
or it will be um
what kind of errors do we want to use i
haven't used used before
uh in this in this stream so maybe let's
use
standard error error
and then we'll use error here
all right so i've i've made a new return
type for this function
and this is result i haven't really
showed generics before but if you've
programmed in languages that have
generics
these angular angle brackets are
saying like um here is i've got a type
and it that type has two type parameters
actually let me just quickly before i
jump to this part because i think
it's important to do the kind of step
right before this
so let's do our enum again
and we'll say this enum it either
succeeds with a value
or it fails okay
so this enum in fact we're going to
write the result enum here
so we need something that says if it
succeeds
uh so when it's okay and when the value
is okay
there is something here and then when it
fails
we'll use error and okay because we'll
see those in a second
so when it succeeds it gets this one
when it fails
it returns this one and we don't know
which one it is again we'll have to
pattern match on it to know
which one and which one succeeds and
which one fails
but at the very least we know we've got
one where it succeeds and one where it
fails
to actually put something in as the
payload
we need to know the type and if we want
this to work over
anything that succeeds and anything that
fails
now we need to use a generic so this
will be actually defining a generic
so we're going to define kind of a will
if you will a success case
and a failure case and this is going to
be the type
that when it succeeds it will give you a
success type
so we'll say success
and when it fails we'll give you a
failure type
all right so these two parameters
we have to parametrize it because we
don't know
what what concrete types what
what types this will be used
with yet we we're just saying they're
generic over these types
and then when you actually create a
result type later
you'll tell me what they are so for
example i could say
let result say
this one is one where it returns i-64 if
it succeeds
or error if it fails
um it may not let me use the term result
here
let me see yeah i might get in trouble
for that
um because result is actually a built-in
let's call it something else like my
result
and my result and there may be another
step but
uh basically yeah let me just check this
real quick
yeah it's complaining it needs to know a
little bit more i really don't want to
go into the details
for this particular example because it
does need a little bit more
but they're a little they're like a few
steps later than we are right now
um but just to kind of squint at it a
bit
you can see that we need a true uh type
and like a failure type
all right with that in mind and again
we can circle back to this later maybe
in an upcoming stream or something
we'll actually unpack why this is
failing now but for now
don't worry about it we'll use the
actual built-in result which is actually
this
but implemented with all the the
the next steps that it would need to
succeed
so we'll say what we're saying process
and that's going to return a result
that is either string or error so here
is same idea
that we had before this is an enum
and the enum has a a success case
and a failure case if it succeeds it
returns a string
if it fails it returns an error
in our process function just for now
we'll use the string.from like was
suggested
we'll just say yay all right so this is
a
result all right did i miss a step
result is a type that represents blah
blah blah the size of the type
oh right see i i should have just
just let me let it tell me what to do
done sized oh i need to say that this is
sorry it's a little extra information
and then i have to say done in here
sheesh
okay there's a lot of
other stuff going on in the background i
could have picked a like a more concrete
error
here i tried to pick like the most
general error
and to use the most general thing you
have to do in a couple extra steps but
fine fair enough same idea applies
there's a success type and now a
slightly more complicated but
basically just saying the same thing an
error and this is
this is like a very generic
error it's saying anything that
satisfies a trait and we'll talk about
traits here in a minute
any time that this thing gets satisfied
that can be returned in this position
thanks russ thanks for keeping me nice
and generic
okay so now
let's call this thing so if i say
let result equal process
you'll notice that the type and this
this colon this type annotation is not
actually in the code
this is just vs code and rust analyzer
giving me a hint as to what the type is
in this location
so it's saying result is a result a
capital capital r result type
and it is string or error
so let's say i wanted to print this out
right my result
is result and it's going to complain
and one of the reasons that it complains
is that
gobbly that we saw before
the same thing i don't know how to print
an enum
and really if i was to try to use this
as a string
so let's say i try to use this as
well in this case i'm kind of trying to
use it as a string
like if this succeeded i would have a
string and this would be valid
how do i get from here where i've got
an error to actually you know
working with this this result type
or working with the string inside of the
result
if it's there and that's where we have
this pattern matching like we did before
so we have like the okay case we'll get
our value out
now you'll see that once we've matched
with ok
right we know it's either okay or air e
r r
so in the okay case we know it's a
string
and now we can just happily print our
our line here with uh x
and the error case we know in this case
this is an error
and you can see that the this box dying
error this uh
thing i was like well i don't know if i
want to get into this quite yet
let's just quickly talk about this box
means that it's on the heap
somewhere i've stored it out on the heap
dying
error means something that implements
the error trait and i don't know what it
is
so something on the heap that is that
implements the error trait i don't know
what it is
i just know it's on the heap but i know
it implements the error trait that's all
it's saying
all right so this error instead of
printing out the air we'll just say
it errored
and call that done oh notice it's
complaining i don't have the
fat error here and now it's
warning me i'm not using it i'm not
gonna i'm just gonna ignore that
cool so now i have called
a function and got a result out and this
pattern
of calling functions that return a
result you'll see it
all the time in russ code because
we don't have exceptions in rust what we
use is this capital r result
to just return values and the values
uh are in that left-hand side of the
result so
whatever we see on the left-hand side of
the comma that's
that's the success case and so
really when you start to read this over
time you kind of
read the name and then you say oh it's a
result okay this success is string
error almost always is something like
this box stein error or something like
some error type that's specific to the
crate or to
doing i o and you can always think of
that as like your error
case in a separate separate part of your
brain
if you will but most of the time you're
just you just want to know what
success is
this match statement is
pretty big if i had to write this all
the time
i'd probably be pretty sad to write russ
code
because this kind of error checking
and dealing with errors that come back
from functions
happens all the time in rust there needs
to be a shorthand
and luckily there is
how's that for cliffhanger
okay so
we have this result and
let's actually use another feature of
rust to get
at the result right the the success case
to do that i'm going to have to change
my main just a little bit
i'll also give the main result case and
i'll also say box
time er
as a result now it's complaining okay
main needs to return some value cool
cool so now
whenever you have a result returned from
a function
you do have to return a result like
it is your responsibility to always
return something
in the success case
and because this result match this match
part of the function didn't really
return anything i just printed out some
values russ will say
you said it returned a result so every
path through that per
every path through that function has to
return a result so we do have to return
a result here
all right now that we turn a result here
you notice the compile errors have gone
away but we still have this
gigantic block of a match statement in
the middle of the function
so let's actually turn this into
something
to get the result and then to use the
result
we just need to use the question mark so
once we use the question mark
let me just show you what it looks like
real quick my result
and we can get this do the same print we
did before
um for the res the success case by doing
it this way
result question mark
all right let's run that
and all of that match statement
is almost completely replaced by a
question mark
so notice this is a lot smaller and in
fact
in practice you wouldn't even write it
like this
you would write it something like this
right even smaller yet so i call the
function
and then this question mark says
if it succeeds give me the value
if it failed so right so we're in the
okay
if it's in the okay case give me the
value if it's in the
error case the err case
then return that immediately out of the
function
so it just bubbles it immediately out
so that's why i had to change the result
type here because
if i use question mark it's going to
return straight out of main
and give me an error
generally on your main you may or may
not use this return type
you may use other functions that return
results and they call other functions
and return results
and so you have this series of functions
that call each other that return result
and then you might have one outside of
all of them
that says okay call them they're all
using question mark
and then the one that is one that's in
main or one that's in your kind of
kernel of functionality
that's the one that does the actual
match and then deals with the errors and
then
prints them to the screen or whatever
but it
cuts down on the amount of boilerplate
that you have to do
to work with errors in your system
is to be able to say for most of the
time
all i need to use is question mark and
i'm just like
looking into that result statement using
the value if it's there if it's not i'm
immediately returning with that error
message
and letting the function that called me
deal with it and then again
it can kind of bubble up so in practice
while not exceptions it feels
as lightweight as exceptions generally
yep
if you don't return a result is any
value implied
no um in fact i think one of the things
that
may change in rust at some point in the
future
is that having to always remember to do
this can be
a bit cumbersome so um
oh i see what you're saying yes yes
andy's right in some cases let me
let me kind of circle back to that in
this particular case
the um you would have to manually say
okay
in this particular case andy's point is
like if i said
like our greet from before notice i
didn't return any types here
this is the same thing as saying this
like
the the type that is empty if that makes
any sense it's uh
doesn't do anything it doesn't it
doesn't have any value
yep you can that that's right that's
technically correct
so you can return that value or
say that the type is that that type and
it means
the empty the empty type
yeah you can do early return manually so
um i did show that you can do like
return
a number here like we could do this
which would be completely meaningless in
this example
but this is an early return and you can
get the value out that way
most of the time i would say that
um well i might i might be making too
broad as a statement i was about to say
most of the time you don't see
early returns that's not true it just
totally depends on the rest code
this style of using question marks is
very common
so error handling and using
this implied earlier early return
via the question mark very common um
maybe less common is like manual returns
and early returns
but maybe more specific to say like it's
in certain patterns you'll see that
rather than more general like you would
in other languages
yep cool
all right so that is
so we talked about structures and
inhuman
enums enums and
a little bit about generics i kind of
threw that in at the last second
but again if you're used to languages
like java or c-sharp
or typescript or anything like that
these generics work very similarly
you just use an angle bracket you pass
them in
and it lets you turn a generic type into
a concrete type
we've done here for result so we turn
this into a specific kind of result
and again here for the result for the
mean
um right structs enums errors generics
cool i think that's a pretty
i did mention traits oh let's have fun
with trades what the heck
what the heck
let me give my voice one second to calm
down while i type
we'll get back to where we were before
with the employee
ah yes right so i was about to do what
we did before
using the curlies to create an employee
but i'm going to stop myself
let me actually write
more like you would do this
in a real program in rest and you do
that
by typing impul
and then the name of the type
generally a struct that you're working
with but it could be other things like
an enum
this is saying not only does this have
does do we have the struct which is data
we have
implementations or methods that go
and connect to this distract
so i can create a new here
and this will return an employee
and now notice i'm using the
style that we had before where it was
an employee and then two parameters
and keep using the string from now i
look at it it's not so bad
um so we'll have a string
that we we can initialize it with so
we'll just say default
and we'll replace this here in a second
and then 100.
so this makes a new function that works
on top of strings
or on top of this struct and we pass in
well we haven't passed it in anything
so this will just create a default
a default value so we'll say
new and now we have our employee
and we could do what we did before we'll
just make a little print statement
and something like this
and this employee will be employee dot
name
oh i might have a typo somewhere i'll go
find it in a second
all right let's run that
cool so you can see i can do something
that feels a little bit more natural
rather than you know always
instantiating the full struct
i can just call new and then have new
fill it out with whatever it feels
is appropriate generally
you'll have a mixture of both of these
but you may have it so that the new
also takes in parameters so let's just
do that real quick
let's just say it takes in a name call
that a string
and then id again i-64
there's a shorthand to using these so i
can
i could say it like this name name id id
like that so that's
completely valid perfectly valid
and then use the
uh what we're going to call this person
employee sure whatever it's funny with
like the things that you pause on
all right there you go so that is
not quite right we need to get our
parentheses in the right place
and what's up oh yeah it's string that
from
okay so
now our new has two parameters this name
and the ide
and then we've called them uh called our
new with these two parameters
and then made a new struct and
initialize it with those
two parameters so you can run that and
get what we'd expect
i was saying earlier that there's
actually a shorter way of typing this if
you're just going to use the same
like the variable and the field are
going to be the same name
you can just use it once and it will
just imply
create the structure and if you're
looking for the value of this field go
find it in for as a variable of the same
name
in the same scope so it's like oh yeah
there is a name
variable i'll just use that an id
variable i'll just use that
and then instance use it so it kind of
saves you some typing
so we have this impul and notice we do
the colon colon here
again this is because
this is not an instance of employee this
is a static
employee but um you'll see
the difference here in a second um
really the key is
is there already something that was
created is there already a value that
we're working with
if not then we'll just call into
this impul this this
the the methods that are on
this um this top level i don't know i'm
trying to figure out an
uh easier way of saying it but i think
there's like
the things that are methods and the
things that aren't methods on an
instance of an object we'll see
we'll see it visually here in one second
okay so we've made
our new to give us employees
right so we can create values of
employees this way
let's make a method that actually uses
this
one common type of method would be a
getter let's just make it getter
for name
right so you might be tempted to write
it like this and get the string out this
way
and then return the string
the problem is there's no this here
right we don't like rust doesn't support
this
um which would be in an instance this is
implied
that there's this this thing and then i
can dot into this
and get the value out
so i use what's called self
and self is a way for this function
to refer to what was
kind of the the instance of this
employee class or employee struct
so i can say self.name and then that
will return
the string but we're about to get a
little
nasty surprise as we do this
and that's totally okay so this
self.name
is indeed a way of referencing in fact
but
before we do that let's actually do um
i'm going to change this real quick but
we'll go back
64 id
and that works
give you a second to think about why
would one
work and one not work but yeah if we
make an
uh a getter for id to return just the
value
for the id from this from the struct
this works okay so we can call instead
of
employee dot id we can call it like this
and call the getter instead
and that gives us our value but when we
try to do this with the string
it didn't work so let's look at that
again
so we'll say name same same pattern same
exact everything
self dot aim but then this one
once i hit save you'll see that it
doesn't work let's hover this and see
why
it says cannot move out of self.name
which is behind a
shared reference move occurs we've got
self.name
has type string which does not implement
the copy trait
now we haven't really seen traits just
yet though we've kind of hinted
at this ability to give types
new functionality and it's saying string
does not have this functionality it
cannot just be
copied and copy here means
that if i refer to this value that i can
without any additional code
on the user's part i know that it's safe
to just
run a function and get the result out
and use the result
behind the scenes that's called copy and
generally it's for
types that are
likely based on the stack they're very
simple types generally
so here an i-64 and an i-64
is the same right there's no there's
nothing
um no heap allocation
nothing about it is really that
complicated and in fact
on the hardware side in a register i can
just store
an i-64 and then when i say move to this
other register
that's a copy right we're not literally
removing it from one
register to another and putting it in
the second register
it's the same kind of idea on the
on the low low level there are a certain
set of types
that copy effortlessly in hardware
and i-64 is one of those so in this case
it's saying
for these set of types these can be
copied by default
for this type this capital string type
it uses the heap
like we talked about before it is not
as easy as you know a little
doing a little bit twiddle in memory
this is something pointing at heap and
if we just naively copied
you know say this this thing is pointing
at the
i'm trying to point it to the camera so
we've got two things
let's say we got one thing pointing into
somewhere in the heap if we naively make
something else that points at the same
thing in the heap now we have
two owners for the same piece of memory
and that is a no no you cannot do that
in rest we need to
give clear ownership so the struct owns
one copy and as you can kind of see
where i'm going
we need a way of saying create me a
whole separate copy
and then give that to whoever called
this function
right so that is why this is erroring
it's saying i can't
do this for you for free you need to do
the extra step
to give a copy of this somewhere else
so i'll say clone
which we have not used before
but clone is going to do
that copy it's going to do a what's
called a clone
which is like a deep copy of the value
and the you know what that pointer is
pointing at on the heap
it's going to give me two separate
versions of that
right the original one and its heap
value
and the new one and its new heap value
that has all the same contents as the
other one right but two separate
ones and that's the important thing so
you've got
two owners and two
roughly equivalent values on the heap
now that we've cloned that this is
correct so we're saying every time we
call new
we get a new string on the heap so you
might feel that this
if you've done a bit of optimization
work or you're you know coming from cnc
plus plus you might think whoa
almost sweat a little bit if you're
going to do an allocation every time i
call this
if you're coming from other languages
maybe not so big a deal you just do this
without thinking about it
i'll show you here how to get around
this in one second
but yeah just for now we're gonna every
time we call
this getter we're just gonna create a
new copy
because it's gonna get us around having
to worry about that
ownership the ownership and borrow
checking
and as a result we can go ahead and run
this
all right there we go now we've made two
getters one that can
get us the name one that can get us the
id
any questions
cool so
let's actually we're going to start
playing a little bit with the borrow
system and because like i said at the
beginning
of the stream you know after i gave some
of the uh
the basics i think one of the things
that people really
trip over is the borrow system
and i want to talk about that and unpack
what's going on
underneath the surface a bit and then
we'll look at a few
techniques that you can use to work with
bio-checking errors that
come up in practice
first let me talk about what um
what this ampersand means because it's
this ampersand is an important thing to
understand as you understand russ code
and what we're saying here is that
when we talk about ownership the way to
think about ownership and
rust another way to think about it
is to say that an owner is who is
responsible for destroying
or deleting that value
so when i look up here
i can see because there are no
ampersands anywhere
that when new is called that ownership
passes into new for the string
and this id
excuse me ownership passes into here
and any ownership that new
has at the end of that function
it will need to delete those values
now in this particular case it doesn't
have to
and the reason is because these two
values
name and id are going to become
owned by this struct so this is going to
take ownership of name and id
because the struct itself needs to get
built right so those are going to come
in
they're going to go right into the
structure and then the structure will
get
returned so after
if i tried to do this
let's say i tried to do let employee
equals oops this
and then we'll return employee down here
but let's say that i tried to also
uh let's see if we can just even try to
print out
what name is here okay
you can see we get an error well we
normally wouldn't get an error
right we can always print out strings
but what we've done is we've said take
name and id
take those two values and stick them
into the struct
right now we have a struct that owns
those values
and that's sitting right here in this
variable employee
right so employee owns those values
name because it doesn't have copy
right it's not that simple copy thing
is com is gone
for for from the perspective of new
at this point in time i have just taken
ownership and said here you go
right it's kind of like i i have a book
and i lent the book to you
uh but in this case i just gave you the
book and then i tried to read the book
later but i don't have the book
i just gave it to you right so employee
now has name and id
it owns these and so you can kind of
think
all of that goes up into the employee
and that's gone
right name is gone and then i when i try
to return it
that's fine i can return the value
that's that's okay
the error is referring to something that
i have already given away
so where were we oh yeah talking about
ownership and
ownership really is who gets to delete
it and who gets to use it
all right so if i given up ownership by
giving it to something else like
employee
i don't get to use it anymore and
at the end of this you know this
function
now is correct because i'm not using
something that i gave up ownership to
the um there's nothing to delete at the
end
right in this particular example had i
not returned
like had i not done this
let's imagine that new looks like this
instead
right if it looked like that then
if i called this the name that came in
and the id that came in would get
deleted at the end of this function
right new owns both of those values
and once the function finishes it's
responsible for cleaning them up
now id is trivial just like it's a copy
a copyable simple type deleting an i64
is like a no op
right there's nothing to do but
name needs its memory freed right it's
pointing at somewhere in the heap
it actually needs to have that memory
freed and this is how
when people say rust does
manual memory management this is the
kind of thing that they're saying
underneath the surface rust is managing
that memory with your help
so if you say this takes ownership it
knows at the end of this function
it needs to call something behind the
scenes
right it's called the drop trait if
anyone wants to go look it up
that will go and clean up that memory so
string
needs cleanup and
you know because again it's got that
pointer to the heat memory that's a
string of characters
no one knows how how big it is um until
you're running this code
so it needs to go and delete those that
that memory for you
that's really where ownership comes in
again is who has to delete this
or who owns the ability to access this
that's another way to think about it
so getting that in mind that when values
come in
to our functions into the structures
um that when they are
when they don't have an ampersand i need
a better name for that
ampersand list doesn't really sound very
nice but if they don't have an ampersand
that means
whoever is getting this value and we can
see up here
same thing right employee gets ownership
of this value when it gets put in
this function gets ownership of name
when it gets called
to avoid that right you're not always
going to want that
you use a borrow and this ampersand
is that it's saying i don't get to own
self like at the end of this getter i'm
not deleting self
right that would be bad a method that
deletes the
the the um the object itself
better be a very specific method that is
not not something you generally want to
do
so this ampersand is saying you get
temporary ownership of this
object or of this value
and at the end of the function rather
than deleting which would be like
full ownership it's just to borrow so i
release
ownership rather than deleting that's
what this is saying
so it comes in and says this ampersa
this uh self is something that i get to
use
there's there's some restrictions in
what i can do to it in this particular
case i can't be
i can't be mutating it or anything like
i can't be changing values in it
all i can do is just look into it i can
peer into it i can get some values out
here you see we go
self dot name no problem we can go and
read a value out
and once we do we can use that value in
some way
here we're calling that method clone on
the result
and getting us a new string out totally
fair game
we can do that at the end of this
function
self the ownership of self passes um
passes back out or you could think of it
a different way like
it's like a a promise to let go of it or
something like that
right so i lent it to you you give it
back to me
that's what we're trying to say here
name uh
we'll give self back to whoever called
us so when we're calling down here
we make our employee object i keep
saying object
think struct when i say object but
generally in your mind that's kind of
what it is underneath the surface right
this instance of employee the struct
object this
uh struct employee employee struct value
right so we have that and when we call
those getters
name will borrow this
okay so this will become the self value
but because we're saying ampersand self
we're saying employee comes in
i get to look at the values and
immediately when it finishes
i just keep going right where i was
before maine never
loses ownership right it just kind of
kind of lets other things borrow it but
the responsibility to destroy like we're
saying
ownership is around who gets to who
who must destroy this at the end of the
function who must clean up the memory
etc
maine never loses that responsibility
it's always going to happen
at the end of maine
so that is um ampersand
so being able to call ampersand self
uh let's just actually real quick do
another another function to show this
um do we need to i mean just for clarity
borrow thing
and then this will take an employee now
if all we've said up to this point is
true
then if we do this
and we use the name that way we can use
it that way
and i say borrow
thing employee
yes the eagle-eyed among you saw that i
did do a typo and that was on purpose
so borrowing is not actually borrowing
yet right
this non-ampersand-less wait
ampersandless non-ampersand whatever you
want to call it
um yeah this is going to take full
ownership of employee so i called this
this thing and then immediately after
that it's like whoa whoa whoa
you moved it right moving means to give
ownership to something else
you gave ownership you moved that value
into being owned by this function
it's gone you don't get to use it
anymore
and to get rid of that error
we use the the ampersand and this will
again mean i get to use it for some
uh short duration i don't own it
right i just borrow it and
we have to change both the definition
of the function and also where it's
called so here
i use the ampersand again to denote this
is a borrow
not a move and it's you know in
designing the language i think
the rust designers are very clever to
make you have to put it both places
because
whether i i'm looking in this part of
the definition you know say this is on
like
file a somewhere and this is in file b
somewhere
regardless of if it's the definition or
the call site i always know
that this is getting borrowed i'm still
responsible
when this thing finishes running i'm
still responsible for employee after
that and i still have access to it
as well so there's the responsibility
and you know
the the power that comes along with that
responsibility
so that is employee and uh
borrowing that employee seeing a
function that that can borrow
this borrow
is actually there is a
us kind of a hidden value that goes
along with this
that says where like who owns this
you could think of it that way um how
long it will live
so it's called a lifetime and
if you get into borrow checking errors
you'll see
lifetime errors where
it says well this thing doesn't live
long enough for this and
and you'll have to kind of deal with
making sure that russ
understands that the lifetimes square up
like
this lives long enough to satisfy
whatever the issue is
let's actually try to get ourselves in a
bit of lifetime
error and then see if we can get back
out
so i'm going to get rid of this borrow
thing
and we'll get rid of this we have the
same pattern up here i just kind of
wanted to expand a little bit to see it
clear
and instead of turning string here
let's return and stir like we are going
to return
now that we now that we've seen
ampersand before
we get a sense for oh this is
like i don't really own this stir it's
owned by someone else somewhere else i
don't know where
necessarily but i know that
this this
string or this in this particular case
it's a
um a string slice like a
a pointer and a length in memory
somewhere pointing at some string of
characters somewhere
we don't know where
but it's owned by someone else
so that ampersand keeps us thinking
about that
the advantage here is that we don't have
to clone anymore
we can say um oh yeah
again we have to use the borrow
we can say go find
you know we've got a struct it's already
got that string in memory
go find where that is and then borrow
that string
right so whoever calls this
now has a borrow of it rather than you
know
two separate strings with two separate
copies in the heap
we have basically one copy in the heap
and two things pointing at it one that's
the owner
and one that's the borrower that makes
sense
and this cuts down on the amount of
work that the your runtime
application needs to do um
but at some you know you do have to
start understanding the borrow system a
little bit to be able to do this
where you know you can describe how who
owns
what and who's borrowing what to the
compiler
i think one of the areas where people
get into trouble
is if they get a little too fancy too
quickly
and don't quite understand the borrower
checker or
get themselves into a corner and i've
done this many many times i'm definitely
definitely just as guilty
i would generally tell people to use
things like clone
first like if you start borrowing
and if you start working with the
ownership system just
know that you're getting into a
territory where you're the
amount of rest that you need to
understand starts to go up a bit
but you can always use clone you can
always make those two copies of the heap
and i'll show a couple other things you
can do there's a thing called
arc arc or using
lock locks over values so that you can
not have to fight the borrower checker
quite so much
i'll show a couple of those here in a
few minutes
but i wanted to show what it looks like
to actually
work with the bar checker directly and
to use it in
the way it's kind of intended so
here i'm i've got that name in the
struct
and so
ampersand self sorry this is a good
clarifying question
so ampersand self.name means
ampersand self.name so like
this just to get some order of
operations clear
yes that's right it means this
it's like go find this member
and then let me borrow that member
yeah exactly it's not borrowing self and
then
dotting into that that's right if you
did
if you did do such a thing
like this
yep so what this does is saying
borrow self and then when i borrow self
dot into it and get the capital s string
out
yeah so we're not actually borrowing the
contents
inside the string or i should say
barring
when you borrow the string you're kind
of borrowing the contents it's a little
it's a little subtle but um yeah this is
this is getting the capital s string out
and what we want is
to borrow inside of that string so yeah
we use
this other form which is either
you can write it like this but generally
you write it the the way that i started
with the ampersand on the outside so
ampersand is like
low low priority everything else happens
first and then you
kind of borrow whatever the result of
that is
yeah that's a great question
all right so now that we've borrowed it
the result of id is still the same
the result of name there we go that's
what we not
is this ampersand stir epperson stir can
be used in a lot of the same ways that
strings can
but it's slightly more efficient right
we're not making that extra copy
we are using the same
the same set of characters or same bytes
in memory
that live inside of employee remember
that
we passed ownership of string and to
employee
that struct is sitting in memory and the
the characters are owned by that struct
and now we have a way of borrowing
those those characters just for long
enough to do this print out
and then at the end of this we'll give
up any borrow
that we've that we've temporarily had
okay
so i'm gonna do i'm gonna expand this
just one more step because i think that
when i saw this i think something
clicked for me that had not
clicked up into that point and i won't
at least show it if you don't
quite get it yet don't worry about it as
you play with rust i think
it will begin to make more sense and
hopefully it'll click for you
but i at least wanted to show it in this
stream because
once you see it i think it begins you
begin to think about
lifetimes as something
very much like a generic type like so
when we write name where we've got
ampersand self
and ampersand stir all right let's
string slice
you've got a borrow coming in and a
borrow going out
how do you know those are the same
borrow
yeah so there's something else going on
here
that tells rust
that the thing that comes in the borrow
of that
and let's let's actually use our words
the lifetime of that borrow the meaning
i'm borrowing something but the owner of
that
says it will live for a certain amount
of time
right the owner has guaranteed a certain
amount of life lifetime for that object
and because that owner has to delete it
at the end of the function
we know that is how long it's going to
live right so anything
that happens has to be
done and dusted by the time that owner
is done owning the object if it doesn't
give it up anywhere else like if it
stays owner the whole time
that's when we know that that
that value is gone it will be deleted
and destroyed
that's the lifetime of
of that object and when we say a borrow
has a lifetime
we're saying the borrow
has kind of a set of information along
with it
that says how long
again that struct or you know that value
behind the scenes
how long that will be available to us
so if we try to do something with it
afterwards
like the type checker that more
specifically the borrower checker
will say oh nope nope lifetimes don't
match
you're trying to borrow this thing for
way longer than it actually is going to
live
so you need something you need some way
of telling me that
what you're doing is actually okay
let's see this let's actually expand
name out
so we can see what name is doing under
the surface
so we'll say um tick
so we saw a t before or you know some
some type variable before
like t is common for type variables tick
a or tick and then sum name
is the name of a lifetime
and again that lifetime is how long the
underlying
thing will live
that is what's actually happening
underneath the surface
so let's let's work through this
rust has seen that something can
comes in with a lifetime tick a
we've actually given it a name now in
before
that was kind of hidden underneath the
surface
and rust was implying this for us and it
saves typing it's great
i think once you understand the
mechanics of how this works
then cool no worries
but if you're not quite up to that point
it can
it can seem a little bit magic that
okay i'm just starting to understand
ownership how does it know when things
are borrowed
for how long and what's going on
sorry let's actually look at this
we are saying that the value that's
coming in itself
is borrowed yeah we knew that
but the underlying thing that we're
borrowing
lives for some lifetime
we've given it a name now called tick a
which just means
some lifetime called tick a just like
when we say a type t and a generic
we're saying some type t we don't know
what it is
in this case we're saying some lifetime
tick a we don't know how long that will
be
the promise that we're making if you
will
to the compiler is that what we're
returning
lives the exact same amount of time
as self right tick a
so we're the thing that comes out is
borrowed
and the underlying thing that is
borrowed lives for
take a lifetime right just like the
thing that comes
that came in is borrowed and lives for
take a lifetime
now if you take a second and think about
this
i think you'll see why this is true
and once you see it i think
some of the ownership systems some of
the borrower system
will start to come into view
the structure that's coming in that
employee structure
right we said before that when we when
we gave
name that string we gave that string to
employee
it owns name right
so everything an employee all the fields
are
are owned by employee in our example
just to kind of remind ourselves right
no ampersands or anything
it owns all those values
when we have self
right self is one of these employees and
we're borrowing it
right take a lifetime right so
some owner somewhere is going to let
that employee value
live for take a lifetime
inside of this employee is that string
and that string lives for the exact same
amount of time
as employee why because employee owns
the name all right you see that
i think once you start to see where
this ownership is happening or where the
the lifetime is happening in this
that when employee is deleted
string is deleted basically at the exact
same time right we're just gonna as we
drop one
we drop all the contents of that string
so
all of that goes away all at the same
time and that's because
employee owns that string that name
field that string
so if we look back here we can kind of
see
all of that machinery that's kind of
behind the scenes
now coming to the surface you give me an
employee
i can safely reach into that employee
and refer to some piece of it i can
borrow some piece of it
if i borrow a piece of it the lifetime
of that piece
has to be the same as the whole thing
because we know employee owns that
that piece
any questions
cool yeah i think
once you wrap your head around this
right i think it helps you unlock how um
yep once yeah once you wrap your head
around it
uh i think it unlocks how all these
pieces start to fit together
uh and the question andy was asking
would lifetime illusion work instead of
ticket yeah so what we used before
is called lifetime religion so instead
of writing it like this
and we wrote it like this
and you'll you'll remember this is
actually what we did
originally right but we didn't know yet
what was happening
beneath the surface so when you see this
imagine what i showed you before
right so the lifetime of self and the
lifetime of this string slice going out
are going to be matched that's that's
lifetime religion and you can kind of
google it and kind of go read about it
but it's
something that the compiler is doing to
save you
from having to type all of the lifetimes
out manually it's kind of like you know
like a language may have type inference
to infer what the type of variable is
lifetime religion is like lifetime
inference
that makes sense right so it's kind of
putting tick a and tick a
here for you without you having to do it
but i think it's i think it's good to
actually
type out um what would be there
without the inference because that lets
you see
how these things are connected
and then once you get used to it then by
all means
by all means use illusion don't save
yourself the typing and save yourself
the complexity a bit
but at least understand what's going on
beneath the surface
so we have a question russ can't figure
out the minimal lifetime of all borrowed
parameters and assign
this to the result to be safe yeah in
the
general case
you cannot imply you can't
infer everything just like in the
general case for type inference
there'll be times when you can't right
you're just in an ambiguous case
just you just don't know which you mean
and in those cases you do have to do the
explicit
lifetime notation
just like you would with like a generic
or what's a good one
there's a method in rus called collect
and collect
can collect into different types of
things
so type inference is ambiguous if you
call collect it's like i
i i don't know what you're trying to
collect well
what are you trying to create and you
have to give it an explicit type
annotation
to say what to collect so that's an
example of
sometimes type inference just doesn't
work right and you have to
you have to use the explicit form the
same thing is going to be true when you
start getting into borrow checking
and borrow like annotations for
lifetimes
sometimes it can imply it it can infer
it i mean sometimes it can infer it and
sometimes you have to be explicit
yep and as we'll see
well i don't know if we'll get into it
in this stream maybe we'll do another
stream
it's like a follow-up but strucks
themselves so here employee was owned
that employee owns this string but you
can imagine that
employee could own a borrow
of you know of a string a borrow of uh
a oh i'm blanking on the name that
the anster basically
so we could it could own something like
that and in that case
the struct needs to hold on to that
information
right as part of its type just like a
type parameter
it would need a lifetime parameter as
well
right so it can't there are some cases
where you do have to be explicit
and then in that explicit information
that's where you know the rust compiler
will will use that
to type check your code or check the
lifetimes of the code
cool any other questions
all right i think the last thing that i
want to do before we call it
is to just point you at a couple of
things that you can use as you start to
explore
the borrower checking
system a bit if you do get stuck
um let me just call these out real quick
oh someone asked to show adding a
dependency
let's let's go do that real quick so
cargo tommel
has these has this dependency
portion of the config file
and in this dependency section
i can just add dependencies into it and
as i do it will go
and fetch these for me there's one i'm
going to use now
called parking lot
incidentally actually let me pull this
up real quick
right you can find these by going to
crates.io
and this is the package registry make
this a little bit bigger so you can see
it
see that okay cool um
i can search for things here so example
if i
tried searching for parking lot you just
have to kind of
this one in particular you just have to
know to look for it
but there's plenty of stuff that you can
just go to the main site
and i do this sometimes just kind of see
what's what's
popular what's newly updated what are
new crates
and then you can look for different
types of things like say you're into
crypto or
you're into async or cli you know
whatever
you're a windows programmer then you can
click in and get
a set of the creates that you might use
as a windows programmer
so this is really handy place to start
to find
what dependencies you could use in your
system
in your application the one we're going
to use is parking lot
in our example and parking lot what it
does
once this pulls up i have to hit enter
apparently who knew um
yeah parking lot is kind of uh
easy to use lock so it's a mutex
and it's got some other stuff in it but
we'll just use the lock part of it
so to add that to our application
what we need to do is to tell cargo
which one we want to use
i've got oh that is something i did not
talk about let's talk about that real
quick
a little sidebar i used a better toml
to give coloring and crates
crates being these dependencies
are called crates
and this plugin for vs code and there
might be similar things for intellij
tell me which ones are up to date and
what their versions are
so i don't have to remember what the
version is i just have to remember oh
yeah there's one called parking lot i
type it in
and i type some quotes where i can auto
complete something and says hey
the latest is 0.11.1 great
cool hit save and you can see that it's
going and
cargo is um running in the background
and we're finding that dependency
downloading it
and checking it so i should now have
uh let me close this
i should now have the ability to call
into parking lot
so here at the top i use standard air
error so this is actually reaching into
the standard crate
and getting values out of the standard
crate
i can use parking lot in the same way
oops parking i type
touched it in the wrong place parking
lot
lock which lock do i want
parking lot oh probably mutex
yeah i want mutex
i think yeah there's actually a few
different ones that we could use
let's just use mutex i think that's what
i wanted to use
and so that's how you go get a
dependency
and then start using that dependency
so i've got i now have a mutex structure
that i can
start to use so let's say that i wanted
to create
a um
like a a thread safe version of a
shared employee and there's
different ways that we can do that but
one one of the easiest ways
is to just put a lock around it
and so any thread that has to use it has
to unlock it first
to use it so we'll make a
locked employee
and we'll say mutex new
i believe i think that's right and the
employee
right so now we have a locked version
i apologize if you can't see that let me
just shrink that up
right so we have a now
an employee we created an employee and
then we gave ownership of that employee
to the mutex so this should look
once i hit save this should look pretty
familiar
hey by the way you moved it
can't do that and yeah yeah we did
we moved it we gave it gave an employee
to the mutex now the mutex is the one
that owns that employee to get the value
back out
we need to actually lock the value
so we'll say um you wouldn't
do this all in one function but i'm just
kind of showing it here for brevity
so our unlocked
employee equals blocked
employee dot
uh unlock
something uh
what am i actually trying to call here
so we made the mutex
i think it's lock try
lock option mutex
guard raw mutex hmm
i'm trying to do this off the top of my
head and i'm kind of blanking on how
this works to be totally honest
with you i want to say that there's a
lock
and then you can just use it yeah
maybe you can just use it at this point
yep that's right
all right so cargo is going while we're
building
you know in the background because we
have these other things
doing the analysis it's already gone and
fetched it if you hadn't done that you
would see it download
the the
parking lot crate and then these are
the steps to build parking lot and now
it runs and this is
actually doing these additional steps
right so we created a mutex
and then we blocked the mutex and got
the employee back out
so this this allows us again to have a
thread save
copy of the employee that multiple
threads can share
so i just kind of want to show this
there is a
a lock or mutex in the standard library
as well you can use you know it's
totally fine to use that one i just use
the parking lot one because there's
one fewer steps in the code
in the one in the standard library you
would need to do a pattern match to make
sure that the lock
locked successfully or failed and then
at that point use the value
but yeah so that's one thing that you
can do is to use
the locks and then the
another trick is to use arc
so let me just show that one real quick
again we're going to give up ownership
of employee to something else
so let's say reference counted
if i say arc new
employee
and we get an error message and says hey
there's a fix for this i kind of like
that uh
but vs code and rust analyzer do this
for you so i don't always have to
remember
where this thing goes sometimes it's
hard to remember where some of these
these values live these structs live
so it's going to import standard sync
arc
and when i do that
i get standard i get the sync arc here
at the top
and now i get this
atomic atomic reference count
i think that's what the a stands for but
this is something else that i can share
right so multiple threads can use this
and
it's going to behind the scenes every
time this is
you know cloned will increment
the count of the number of people
referring to it so you can safely know
when you can modify it or when you can't
because if more than one person's
looking at it
you know it's not safe to be modifying
it right there's
there's you know six eyes on this thing
uh if you start mutating it they're
gonna see
some kind of weird behavior and so in
rust
i kind of implied this before but let's
just kind of
say it out explicitly you can have
multiple borrows
of something if they're immutable
right so each borrow always sees the
same
value whenever they look at it for as
long as that borrower lives
so you can have multiple borrows so long
as they're immutable
if you have a mutable borrow you can
only have
one only one person is allowed to
observe
and mutate a value
and this gets you out of trouble of
all kinds of stuff more than we have
time to go for into in this stream
but that that's a simplifying assumption
that in the rust type system and the
ownership system
that's how they keep threads safe you
know
yeah sure you can share it but you can't
mutate it or if you mutate it
you need to only have one owner and the
tricks that using mutex
and arc give you are to how do you know
that there's only one owner
mutex lets you lock it now you have one
um one wave looking into it
right everyone that wants to look in has
to lock it first
only one person gets to win and that
person also
could get to mutate it right they're the
one owner or the one
i guess you could kind of say like the
one borrower
one mutable borrower so that's
why mutex works and then arc works by
doing this counting
so if you try to mutate and multiple
people have borrowed it
that will fail right so it's kind of
doing the same
kind of enforcement but it's enforcing
it at run time
right every time you peer into this arc
you have
you get a little reference count or
every time you own
a copy of this arc you get a reference
count and that reference count is what's
keeping you
safe okay i wanted to at least mention
those two they are a little bit more
advanced
but as you get into the borrowed
checking system
having tools like just cloning it
don't worry about the copies that's
always the option right you can always
do that
if you want to keep one value in memory
and say it's like a big object or
something that you really don't want
multiple copies of
you can use locking you can use arcs to
not have to worry
about really fine-tuning
all your all your lifetime annotations
everywhere you can use these other tools
to get going and to get working